1.1 The Name of the Game

1.1.1 TeX
TEX is a computer program created by Donald E. Knuth. 
It is aimed at typesetting text and mathematical formulae. 
TEX as we use it today was released in 1982, with some slight enhancements added in 1989 to better support 8-bit characters and multiple languages. 
TEX is renowned for being extremely stable, for running on many diﬀerent kinds of computers, and for being virtually bug free. 
The version number of TEX is converging to π and is now at 3.141592653


1.1.2 LaTeX
LATEX enables authors to typeset and print their work at the highest typographical quality, using a predeﬁned, professional layout. 
It uses the TEX formatter as its typesetting engine





1.2 Basics

1.2.1 Author, Book Designer and Typesetter
To publish something, authors give their typed manuscript to a publishing company
One of their book designers then decides the layout of the document (column width, fonts, space before and after headings ...)
The book designer writes his instructions into the manuscript and then gives it to a typesetter, who typesets the book according to these instructions.
A human book designer tries to ﬁnd out what the author had in mind while writing the manuscript.

LATEX takes the role of the book designer and uses TEX as its typesetter. 
But LATEX is “only” a program and therefore needs more guidance. 
The author has to provide additional information to describe the logical structure of his work. 
This information is written into the text as "LaTeX commands"
(nota: WYSIWYG = What You See Is What You Get)

1.2.2 Layout Design
With WYSIWYG systems, authors often generate aesthetically pleasing documents with very little or inconsistent structure. 
LATEX prevents such formatting errors by forcing the author to declare the logical structure of his document. 
LATEX then chooses the most suitable layout

1.2.3 Advantages and Disadvantages
  + Professionally crafted layouts are available, which make a document really look as if “printed.”
  + The typesetting of mathematical formulae is supported in a convenient way
  + Easy to use, lots of packages, highly portable and free
  + LATEX encourages authors to write well-structured texts, because this is how LATEX works — by specifying structure
  - Although some parameters can be adjusted within a predeﬁned document layout, the design of a whole new layout is diﬃcult and takes a lot of time
  - It is very hard to write unstructured and disorganized documents
  - Your hamster might, despite some encouraging ﬁrst steps, never be able to fully grasp the concept of Logical Markup





1.3 LaTeX Input Files

1.3.1 Spaces
 - “Whitespace” characters, such as blank or tab, are treated uniformly as “space” by LATEX. 
Several consecutive whitespace characters are treated as one “space.” 
Whitespace at the start of a line is generally ignored, and a single line break is treated as “whitespace.” 
 - An empty line between two lines of text defines the end of a paragraph. 
Several empty lines are treated the same as one empty line. 



1.3.2 Special Characters 
The following symbols are reserved characters that either have a special meaning under LATEX or are not available in all the fonts. 
If you enter them directly in your text, they will normally not print, but rather coerce LATEX to do things you did not intend. 
# $ % ^ & _ { } ~ \ 
As you will see, these characters can be used in your documents all the same by using a prefix backslash:
\# \$ \% \^{} \& \_ \{ \} \~{} 
\textbackslash



1.3.3 LaTeX Commands
LATEX commands are case sensitive (distingue mayuscula o minuscula) and take one of the following two formats:
  - They start with a backslash \ and then have a name consisting of letters only. Command names are terminated by a space, a number or any other ‘non-letter.’ 
  - They consist of a backslash and exactly one non-letter.
  - Many commands exist in a ‘starred variant’ where a star is appended to the command name.

LATEX ignores whitespace after commands. 
If you want to get a space after a command, you have to put either an empty parameter {} and a blank or a special spacing command after the command name. 
The empty parameter {} stops LATEX from eating up all the white space after the command name. Ej:
  - MAL: New \TeX users may miss whitespaces after a command.
  + BIEN: Experienced \TeX{} users are \TeX perts, and know how to use whitespaces

Some commands require a parameter, which has to be given between curly braces { } after the command name. 
Some commands take optional parameters, which are inserted after the command name in square brackets [ ].
\command[optional parameter]{parameter}. 
Ejemplos:
\textsl{texto}  ---->  texto aparece en cursiva
\newline



1.3.4 Comments
When LATEX encounters a % character while processing an input file, 
it ignores the rest of the present line, the line break, and all whitespace at the beginning of the next line.





1.4 Input File Structure
When LATEX processes an input ﬁle, it expects it to follow a certain structure. 
Thus every input ﬁle must start with the command \documentclass{...}
This specfies what sort of document you intend to write. 
After that, add commands to inﬂuence the style of the whole document, or load packages that add new features to the LATEX system. 
To load such a package you use the command \usepackage{...}

When all the setup work is done, you start the body of the text with the command \begin{document} 
Now you enter the text mixed with some useful LATEX commands. 
At the end of the document you add the \end{document} command, which tells LATEX to call it a day. 
Anything that follows this command will be ignored by LATEX








