2.4 PUTTING BLOCKS TOGETHER

Once you have the blocks, as we said before, you need to append them. 
The mappend method of the Monoid class does this work. If a and b are two blocks, mappend a b, or a ‘mappend‘ b, or even a <> b, is the block with a and b juxtaposed.
(<>) is defined as a synonym for mappend 
For long lists of blocks, you can try it with mconcat as follows

mconcat [ "I can see a " , textbf "rainbow" , " in the blue " , textit "sky" , "." ]





2.5 RENDERING

This is the last step in our LATEX document creation. 
When we have our final LATEX block a, the function renderFile can output it into a file, 
in the form of its correspondent LATEX code.

Say we have the next definition

short = 
   documentclass [] article 
<> title "A short message" 
<> author "John Short" 
<> document (maketitle <> "This is all.")


Then, after calling
 
renderFile "short.tex" short

the following file appears in the current working directory (line breaks added for easier visualization):


\documentclass{article} 
\title{A short message} 
\author{John Short} 
\begin{document} 
\maketitle{} 
This is all 
\end{document}

Finally, you may use commands like latex or pdflatex to compile the LATEX output to dvi or pdf.



2.5.1 Render class:
The function renderFile is not only for LaTeX values. Let’s see its type:

renderFile :: Render a => FilePath -> a -> IO ()
         
The Render class that appears in the context is deﬁned:

class Render a where 
render :: a -> Text


So, it is the class of types that can be rendered to a Text value. 
The type LaTeX is an instance, but other types, like Int or Float, so are too. 
These instances are useful for creating blocks from other values. 
With the function rendertex, any value in the Render class can be transformed to a block. 
First, the value is converted to Text, and then to LaTeX the same way we did with strings. 
But, be careful! Because rendertex does not escape reserved characters.


  