2.2 LaTeX blocks

Suppose we have a well-formed piece of LATEX code, call it a  
(well-formed meaning that all braces, environments, math expressions, ... are closed.)
Then, a can be seen as a Haskell expression a of type LaTeX. We can say that a is a LaTeX block.


What happens if we append, by juxtaposition, two LaTeX blocks? 
As both are well-formed, so is the result. Thus, two blocks appended form another block. 
This way, we can deﬁne an operation over the LaTeX blocks. 
If we consider that a totally empty code is a well-formed piece of LATEX code, we can speak about the empty block. 
And, as the reader may notice, these blocks with its appending form a monoid. 
Namely, LaTeX can be done an instance of the Monoid class.


Of course, our mission using HATEX is to create a LaTeX block that ﬁts our purpose. 
The way to achieve this is to create a multitude of LaTeX blocks and, then, 
use the Monoid operation to collapse them all in a single block.