Usaremos funciones, por ejemplo

delta :: LaTeX
linespread :: Float -> LaTeX
title :: LaTeX -> LaTeX

And this is, essentialy, the way to work with HATEX: to create blocks and combine them.
Once you have your ?nal block ready, you will be able to create its corresponding LATEX code (we will see how later). 
Note that for every block there is a LATEX code, but not for every code there is a block, 
because a malformed (in the sense of the negation of our well-formed concept) code has not a block in correspondence. 
This fact has a practical consequence: we cannot create malformed LATEX code. 
And that’s a good deal!



2.3.1 From Strings
 You can create a block with text given an arbitrary String with the fromString function, 
method of the IsString class:

class IsString a where
   fromString :: String -> a

Since there is a set of characters reserved to create commands or another constructions, 
HATEX takes care and avoids them replacing each reserved character with a command which output looks like the original character. 
For example, the backslash \ is replaced with the \backslash{} command.

The function that avoids reserved characteres is exported with the name protectString.
Also, there is a variant for Text values called protectText.

The use of the IsString class is because the Overloaded Strings extension. 
This one is similar to the Overloaded Numbers Haskell feature, which translates the number 4 to fromInteger 4. 
In a similar way, with OverloadedStrings enabled, the string "foo" is translated to fromString "foo". 
If we now apply this to our blocks, the string "foo" will be automatically translated to a latex block with foo as content. 
Quite handy! We will assume the OverloadedStrings extension enabled from now



2.3.2 More Blocks
There is a lot of functions for create blocks. 
In fact, we can say that this is the main purpose of the library. 
LATEX has a lot of commands, in order to set font attributes, create tables, insert graphics,include mathematical symbols,etc. 
So HATEX have a function for each command deﬁned in LATEX (to tell the truth, only for a small subset). 
Please, go to the API documentation to read about particular functions. 
Build it locally or ﬁnd it in Hackage: http://hackage.haskell.org/package/HaTeX. 
You will ﬁnd the class constraint LaTeXC l in every entity. 
LaTeX is an instance of this class, so you can assume that l is the LaTeX datatype without any problem.
More about this in section about the LaTeXC class.



 


